Guide to the Clay Felker Papers, 1945-1996
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Clay Felker papers 1945-1996
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Felker, Clay.
14.0 linear feet Extent: 9000 Items
Clay Felker (1925-2008) was an editor and publisher who edited magazines such as New York Magazine (which he founded in 1968), New West Magazine, Village Voice, and Esquire. Collection includes materials from Felker's journalism career, with the bulk of the materials dating from 1968 through 1981. The majority of the materials relate to Felker's publishing and editorial work on New York Magazine, New West Magazine, Village Voice, Esquire, and Daily News Tonight. Included are story ideas and correspondence with various writers and editors; drafts of articles and columns; contract and legal negotiations; correspondence from Felker's fans and friends; budgetary materials; press clippings and news coverage; and other miscellaneous materials. Also includes copies of Duke University Chronicle, 1948-1952, dating from Felker's years as a writer and editor; copies of The Blue Jacket, 1944-1945, dating from Felker's years as a sports editor; some personal correspondence and materials from Felker's friends and family; and some other miscellaneous material.
RL.00386
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Clay Felker Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2010.
Biographical Note
Chronology List
1925 October 2 Born, Webster Grove, Mo.
1942 Entered Duke University
1943 Left Duke University to join the Navy
1948 Editor, Duke Chronicle newspaper
1948 Expelled from Duke for staying out with his date, Leslie Blatt, past the Women's College curfew
1949 Married Leslie Blatt
1950 Re-enrolled at Duke University
1951 Graduated Duke University
1950-1951 Worked as a statistician with New York Giants broadcasting
1951-1954 Sports writer for Life magazine
1954 Helped develop Sports Illustrated
1954-1957 Political reporter in Washington for Life magazine
1957-1962 Features editor, Esquire
1962 Married Pamela Tiffin, an actress and fashion model
1963-1967 Editor, New York, the Sunday supplement magazine of the New York Herald Tribune
1966 Herald Tribune, World-Telegram and Sun, and Journal-American merged into the World Journal Tribune
1967 World Journal Tribune folded; Felker purchased naming rights to New York
1969-1976 Editor, New York magazine
1969 Divorced Pamela Tiffin
1971 December New York issue included an insert of selections from Ms. magazine
1972 January Funded first stand-alone issue of Ms. magazine
1974 New York Magazine Company merged with The Village Voice; Felker became editor of The Village Voice
1975 New York spin-off, New West, began publishing in California
1976 Lost control of New York Magazine Company to Rupert Murdoch; resigned as editor of New York
1977 August Purchased Esquire magazine; became Esquire editor
1979 Sold Esquire magazine; resigned as editor
1980-1981 Editor, The Daily News Tonight, a division of The New York Daily News
1980-1981 Producer, 20th Century Fox
1981-1982 Editor, AdWeek
1984 Married Gail Sheehy, a writer
1987-1990 Editor, Manhattan Inc. magazine
1994 Lecturer, University of California at Berkeley
2008 July 1 Died, New York City, New York
Subject Headings
Felker, Clay; Murdoch, Rupert, 1931-; New York Magazine Company; Duke University -- Periodicals; New York (New York, N.Y.); Esquire (New York, N.Y.); Ms.; Village voice (Greenwich Village, New York, N.Y.); 20th Century-Fox; Periodicals -- Publishing -- United States; Periodicals -- Editing -- United States; Editors -- Correspondence; Men's magazines -- Editing; Journalism -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Nonfiction novel -- History and criticism; Editors -- United States
Collection Overview
Collection includes materials from Felker's journalism career, with the bulk of the materials dating from 1968 through 1981. The majority of the materials relate to Felker's publishing and editorial work on New York magazine, New West magazine, Village Voice, Esquire, and Daily News Tonight. The collection contains the publications' annual reports, financial projections and budgets, circulation and advertising plans, and materials from stockholder questionnaires and meetings. Also included are story ideas and correspondence with various writers and editors, as well as drafts of articles and columns. Many materials are anonymous and undated, because the author's name is missing from Felker's version of the draft. Some writers and journalists represented in the collection include George Dennison, Benjamin Sonnenberg, Gail Sheehy (Felker's third wife), Aaron Latham, Robert Karen, Thomas Thompson, Arnold Beichman, Jimmy Breslin, Jane O'Reilly, Andrew Tobias, and many more.
Other magazine-related materials include contract and legal negotiations, particularly regarding Felker's launch of New York; his loss of New York and Village Voice; his acquisition of Esquire, The Advertiser, and AdWeek; and his subsequent loss of Esquire. Correspondence between Felker and various law firms involved in these sales and mergers is also included. There are also many letters, both congratulatory and condoling, reacting to his various career changes. Many of his friends and fans were powerful figures in the publishing world, including George Lang, Marianne Partridge, Peter Derow, Felix Rohatyn, Tom Wolfe, Gloria Steinem, Herb Goro, and Malcolm Forbes.
Press clippings covering Felker's career are also present in the collection, beginning with his early journalism career in the 1960s, but heavily covering his various publication acquisitions and activities as editor of New York, New West, Village Voice, Esquire, and The Daily News Tonight. Besides reporting on the acquisitions, these clippings also include profiles of Felker as well as evaluations and criticisms of his work. One subcomponent of the clippings includes coverage of the 1976 CIA press leak by Daniel Schorr to the Village Voice and the subsequent Congressional investigations.
The collection also includes files and materials from Felker's years as a producer at 20th Century Fox, where he proposed and developed story ideas for television and movies. The files include synopses of proposed scripts as well as expense reports for some of the research and travel he undertook.
The remainder of the collection is somewhat miscellaneous in content. There are issues of The Blue Jacket, 1944-1945, dating from Felker's years as a sports editor. Also represented are Felker's years at Duke, including his articles and editorials in a few issues of The Archive and Duke 'n' Duchess, as well as bound copies of the Duke University Chronicle, 1948-1952, dating from Felker's years as a writer and editor. There are also small amounts of correspondence and reports from some of Felker's other interests and ventures, many of which never went past the planning stages. There is some personal correspondence and materials from Felker's friends and family, dating largely from the 1970s, and some other miscellaneous material.
Contents of Collection
- Accession (2010-0207), 1944-1996, (10 boxes)
  - Blue Jacket, July 1944-March 1945, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    Military newspaper with issues featuring Felker as Sports Editor.
  - The Archive (Duke University), February 1948-April 1948 (Box 1)
    Magazine issues with articles written by Felker.
  - Duke 'N' Duchess (Duke University), September 1948-December 1948 (Box 1)
    Magazine issues featuring Felker as Assistant Editor.
  - Correspondence, Duke-related, 1948 (Box 1)
  - Article drafts by Felker, 1956 and undated (Box 1)
  - Casey Stengel's Secret, 1961 (Box 1)
    Book written by Felker.
  - Felker News Service reports, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Teen magazine plans, undated (Box 1)
  - International Intelligence Report, 1962-1963, (3 folders) (Box 1)
    Memos, plans, correspondence, etc.
  - Research and Reportage, Inc., 1963-1968 (Box 1)
  - The Girl of the Year movie plot, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, miscellaneous, pre-1967 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous stories edited by Felker, undated, (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - World Journal Tribune, 1967 (Box 1)
    Regarding the shut-down of its Sunday feature, New York Magazine.
  - Capital, 1967 (Box 1)
    Correspondence between Felker and Adolph Theobald about setting up an independent magazine.
  - Cheetah magazine venture, for people under 30, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Duke University, 1967-1976 (Box 1)
    Alumni affairs and donations.
  - Correspondence, re: Felker family, 1968-1977 (Box 1)
    Includes condolence letters following the death of Felker's father, and recommendation letters for Felker's nephew.
  - Scheduling and invite lists, 1967-1975 (Box 1)
    Guest lists for events, including New York Magazine and Village Voice programs.
  - Clippings and press coverage, 1960s-1975, (9 folders) (Box 1)
    Coverage of Felker, his career, and his various publications.
  - Clippings and press coverage, 1975-1977, (4 folders) (Box 2)
  - Phone log books, 1977-1979, (4 folders) (Box 2)
  - Battle, Fowler, Stokes, and Kheel, 1968-1977 (Box 2)
    Includes correspondence and transcripts with Felker and Theodore Kheel, a lawyer who worked with Felker and the New York Magazine Company.
  - Summer house, 1969-1975 (Box 2)
    Leases, etc., for house rentals on Long Island, N.Y.
  - Miscellaneous article by George Dennison, undated (Box 2)
  - Correspondence and articles by Benjamin Sonnenberg, undated (Box 2)
  - Correspondence and articles by or about Lally Weymouth, 1976 and undated (Box 2)
  - Pamela Tiffon/Clay Felker divorce, 1967-1975 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence and clippings by Gail Sheehy, 1972-1976 (Box 2)
  - The Colonel, undated, (4 folders) (Box 2)
    Draft by Marge Crumbaker and Gabe Tucker.
  - Herald Tribune's New York magazine (Sundays), 1965 (Box 3)
  - New York magazine
    - Founding and planning, 1968 (Box 3)
    - Annual reports, 1969-1975 (Box 3)
    - Budgets and budget projections, 1967-1974, (4 folders) (Box 3)
    - Stockholder meetings, 1970-1973 (Box 3)
    - Annual issues, 1971-1972 (Box 3)
    - Editorial memos, 1974-1976 (Box 3)
      Internal correspondence between Felker and his editors, including discussions of the magazine's news coverage, etc.
    - Flow of Reading study, 1975 (Box 3)
    - Bonuses/salaries, 1975 (Box 3)
    - Circulation, 1971-1975, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Legal guidelines, 1975-1976 (Box 3)
    - Stockholders Questionnaire, 1976 (Box 3)
    - Board of Directors, 1971-1976 (Box 3)
    - Copyright, 1973-1976 (Box 3)
    - Agreements between Felker and Carter Burden, 1975 (Box 3)
    - Advertising reports, 1975-1976 (Box 3)
    - Drafts of articles, 1970s and undated, (3 folders) (Box 3)
      Reporters and writers represented inclue Arnold Beichman, Paul Gardner, Robert Karen, Aaron Latham, Barth Schwartz, Charles Sopkin, and Thomas Thompson.
    - Story ideas and other drafts, 1968-1976, (4 folders) (Box 3)
      Reporter, writer, editor, and agency correspondence with Clay Felker for New York Magazine articles and ideas, including Ken Auletta, John Berendt, Jimmy Breslin, John Bryson, Jon Carroll, Rasa Gustaitis, Anthony Haden-Guess, George Harris, Judith Kipper, Joan Kron, Aaron Latham, Leonard Mosley, Jane O'Reilly, Richard Reeves, Edgar Scherick, Gail Sheehy, Andrew Tobias, and John Walsh.
    - Draft of Abraham Michael Rosenthal/New York Times profile, undated (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, with Tony Mayer, 1976 (Box 3)
  - Ms. magazine, Felker's personal finances, 1972-1975 (Box 3)
  - MAC/Jim Kelly, 1973-1975 (Box 3)
  - Felker's employment contracts, 1972-1976 (Box 3)
    Includes negotiations and contracts for New York magazine and Village Voice.
  - Village Voice stockholders, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Clippings and coverage of the Village Voice's CIA leak with Daniel Schorr, 1976, (3 folders) (Box 4)
  - New West finances and advertisements, 1975-1976, (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - New West clippings and coverage, 1976 (Box 4)
  - New West story ideas, 1976 (Box 4)
  - New West Magazine, 1980 (Box 4)
  - Research reports, New York Magazine Company, 1975-1976 (Box 4)
  - Murdoch's purchase of New York Magazine Company, 1976 (Box 4)
  - L'Express, 1977 (Box 4)
  - Stigwood Group, 1977-1978 (Box 4)
    Includes contracts, correspondence, and other materials from the joint venture between Felker and Stigwood Group for literary and movie projects.
  - The American Lawyer, 1978-1979 (Box 4)
  - Esquire
    - Felker's purchase of Esquire, 1977 (Box 4)
    - Congratulatory letters, 1977 (Box 4)
      Includes correspondence from Dorothy Monet, George Lang, Marianne Partridge, Peter Derow, Richard Wald, Felix Rohatyn, Terry Gwyn, David Brown, Barrett Gallagher (includes photograph portfolio), Herb Goro, Albert Goldman, and Malcolm Forbes.
    - Press clippings and coverage of Esquire, 1977-1979, (3 folders) (Box 4)
    - Reports and finances, 1978-1979 (Box 4)
    - Board of Directors reports and finances, 1977-1979 (Box 4)
    - Sale, 1978-1979 (Box 4)
    - Purchase of N.E. Corporation, 1979 (Box 4)
    - Mail about Esquire, 1977-1979 (Box 5)
      Includes general fan mail as well as condolence notes for Felker after losing Esquire; writers include Gary Trudeau, Geoffrey Norman, Gloria Steinem, and Ted Hearne.
  - Felker Communications Inc., 1979-1982 (Box 5)
    Correspondence regarding the purchase of other papers.
  - Winslow Maxwell and Partners, invoices and correspondence, 1978-1981 (Box 5)
  - The Advertiser, 1978-1981, (3 folders) (Box 5)
    Includes materials from its purchase by Felker, insurance papers, content, advertising, profits, and employees.
  - AdWeek, 1981-1982, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    Includes materials on its columns and finances.
  - East Bay Newspapers, Inc., 1981-1982 (Box 5)
  - Travel expenses, 1979-1982, (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Expenses, 1967-1978, (13 folders) (Box 5)
  - Duke Chronicle clippings, 1948-1951 (Box 6)
  - Broadside Art, Inc., 1967-1968 (Box 6)
  - Clay Felker Publications, 1967-1969 (Box 6)
  - London magazine project, 1972-1974 (Box 6)
  - New York magazine office furniture, 1974-1976 (Box 6)
  - Riverdale Press acquisition, 1977 (Box 6)
  - Speeches and articles by Felker, 1968-1979, (3 folders) (Box 6)
  - Village Voice
    - Thesis on its history, 1973 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence and reports, 1974 and undated (Box 6)
    - Promotions and advertising, 1974 (Box 6)
    - Subscriber surveys and lawsuit, 1973-1975 (Box 6)
  - Los Angeles Herald Examiner, 1980 (Box 7)
  - Daily News Tonight
    - Employment, 1980-1981 (Box 7)
    - Congratulatory letters, 1981 (Box 7)
    - Press clippings and coverage, 1980-1981, (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - Focus groups, editorials, and plans, 1980 (Box 7)
    - Operations, 1980 (Box 7)
    - Promotions and advertising, 1980-1981 (Box 7)
    - Name files, A-F, 1980-1981, (3 folders) (Box 7)
      Name files include correspondence, story ideas, notes, clippings, and drafts from Felker's time at Daily News.
    - Name files, G-Z (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, Mike O'Neill, 1980-1981 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, Liz Smith, 1980-1981 (Box 8)
    - Stigwood Group story, 1981 (Box 8)
    - Expenses, 1980-1981 (Box 8)
  - 20th Century Fox producing (Box 9)
    - Active story numbers, 1980 (Box 9)
    - Submissions, 1979-1980 (Box 9)
    - Rejections, 1979-1980 (Box 9)
    - Untitled Brazilian Rock and Roll (Rio), with Aaron Latham, (2 folders) (Box 9)
    - Hip Capitalism, with writer Jack Nessel (Box 9)
    - Jacques Mesrine story, with writer Harry Stein (Box 9)
    - Lisa Lyon, body building (Box 9)
    - Mob Lawyer, with Steven Brill (Box 9)
    - Preppie, 1980 (Box 9)
    - Redneck Riviera, with Geoffrey Norman, 1980 (Box 9)
    - Super Thief, with Tom Zitto, 1980 (Box 9)
    - Woman of the Year, undated (Box 9)
    - Woman Who Has Everything, 1967 (Box 9)
    - Weekly advance to producer reports, 1979-1980 (Box 9)
    - General correspondence and miscellaneous movies, 1980-1981 (Box 9)
    - Movie studio funding, undated (Box 9)
    - Los Angeles to New York trips, 1980 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence, personal, 1980 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence, Richard Berger, 1980 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence, Claire Townsend, 1980 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence, Dennis Stanfill, 1980 (Box 9)
  - Notebooks, 1993 and undated (Box 9)
  - Exclusive right to sell, New York apartment, 1996 (Box 9)
  - Duke University Chronicle, 1948-1952 (Box 10)
    Oversize bound issues from Felker's career at the Chronicle.